<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kostya&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://xni.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kostya&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 22:17:11 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://xni.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Will the exchanges survive?</title>
        <link>https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 22:17:11 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/</guid>
        <description>Kostya&#39;s Blog https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/ -&lt;p&gt;Citadel Securuties &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/ken-griffin-s-virus-plan-now-includes-emergency-site-in-florida&#34;&gt;placed&lt;/a&gt; its high profile traders to the isolated hotel in Florida. I am not saying this post will be truth. It is just a reflection of my knowledge about finance, how I have connected the dots of facts known by me to a broader picture. Probably, some guys like Ray Dalio etc etc has a better clarity about all of these, but I will try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why the exchanges remained open during the coronavirus outbreak?
I think the answer lies in the realization how deep we are drawn into the &amp;lsquo;investments&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investments were there for a very long time. Mostly in the form of fundraising:
trading ships, manufacturing and even wars. It was necessary back in the days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And profitable. Can you imagine an old farmer of X-th century dreaming about passive income?
Probably, not. But actually he usually was doing a good investments in another way: children.
Seriously, if you have lots of children who are healthy, not lazy, strong, they will care
about you when you will get older. So helping them to grow up was a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But later on, we have moved from the agricultural society to the manufacturing one.
And capitalists entered the game. Generally, if you were able to accumulate some capital,
you can live by running your factory, by creating jobs. And being a capitalist was
a way to create a passive income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, some people realized, that even if you don&amp;rsquo;t have enough funds to open a
factory by your own, you can own a factory together. And here we are welcoming a
stock exchanges, first IPOs and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, things are logical to me.
So, what we observed was: we need exchanges in order to people who want to invest now,
in order to receive some money flow in the future, can meet each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea became so popular, that now everyone is an investor.
Because our goverments are literally telling us - you don&amp;rsquo;t have any other way
to have a chance to retire other than being an investor. We will not care about you.
Your children will not care about you. Only participating in some capitalistic
businesses is a way to have your payments in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why the exchange in my opinion is equal to the capitalism.
If the goverment orders to close NASDAQ, it will move us back to square one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens some other interesting questions: how durable is this model? Generally,
if everyone will become an investor, investing 90% of their money to something,
how profitable it will be? If we will be spending money only on food and
building material for our houses, what can we invest to? Only to agriculture
and building. These will be the only businesses. And then, you will also work
only there. It looks like a loop. And we are back to square 1. That&amp;rsquo;s why we
need some money spoiling habits, because they free some money from the system,
it is a way to create slavery from the people who prefer to spend now rather than
to spend. Please, love them. They and their children will work in order to
make your retirement smooth and happy.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 