<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kostya&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://xni.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kostya&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 21:14:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://xni.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Reading through HEX</title>
        <link>https://xni.github.io/tech/hex-reading-interesting-facts/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 21:14:00 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://xni.github.io/tech/hex-reading-interesting-facts/</guid>
        <description>Kostya&#39;s Blog https://xni.github.io/tech/hex-reading-interesting-facts/ -&lt;p&gt;Right now I am improving our exchange connectivity libraries.
And one of the regular activities is anaylzing tcpdumps to validate what was sent over the wire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing this for nearly for the whole week I found couple of tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;jumping-to-the-end-of-frame&#34;&gt;Jumping to the end of frame&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have some frame-oriented protocol, like websocket
or EUREX ETI. Usually, message in those protocols start from the
&lt;code&gt;message_size&lt;/code&gt; field, then the message body follows, then the next
message and so on. So, if you want to jump from message N to the
message N+1 you need to skip message-size bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say this is our tcpdump:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;48 00 00 00 01 02 03 04  ab cd ef f0 fe dc ba 98
00 00 11 12 45 9c 2a 23  62 22 b0 c1 38 52 55 6a
bb 52 21 01 34 a5 50 32  ba 51 b6 81 84 42 24 bb
13 ac 52 52 62 12 00 00  11 35 73 ba 51 62 72 31
58 25 40 00 30 00 00 11  31 00 62 65 bc bc 62 11
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;code&gt;48 00 ...&lt;/code&gt; is the message size. Where does the second message starts from?
Before figuring out the first hack I was doing the following: 48 hex = 72 dec.
Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s count 72 characters&amp;hellip; so the next message is &lt;code&gt;31 00 ...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I figured out eventually is that hexdump renders 16 bytes per line, so
48 in hex actually means - to find the beginning of a next message skip 4 rows
and 8 columns. That&amp;rsquo;s it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;decoding-ascii-from-hex-in-mind&#34;&gt;Decoding ascii from hex in mind&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the protocols are binary, but some are textual. &lt;code&gt;hexdump -C&lt;/code&gt; is a nice thing
display both, but from time to time there are situations where you have just a wall
of hex bytes. Turned out that there are some easy rules you can decode text from the
ascii bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what I ended up with: 30 in hex actually means &amp;lsquo;0&amp;rsquo;. It is very convinient. All of
the hex numbers in the range 30-39, just drop &amp;lsquo;3&amp;rsquo;, and you have a digit.
40 - is a character &amp;lsquo;before&amp;rsquo; the alphabet. So that &amp;ldquo;the first letter&amp;rdquo; - so 40 + 1, is &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo;.
So, it is easy to decode 41-46 as &amp;lsquo;A&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;B&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;C&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;D&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;E&amp;rsquo; accordingly. 60 - is a character
&amp;lsquo;before&amp;rsquo; the lower-case alhpabet. 61 is &amp;lsquo;a&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://xni.github.io/tech/hex-reading-interesting-facts/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>GDB basics</title>
        <link>https://xni.github.io/tech/gdb-basics/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:50:00 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://xni.github.io/tech/gdb-basics/</guid>
        <description>Kostya&#39;s Blog https://xni.github.io/tech/gdb-basics/ -- https://xni.github.io/tech/gdb-basics/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>GDB basics</title>
        <link>https://xni.github.io/tech/vscode-bash-vs-ssh-bash/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 07:50:00 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://xni.github.io/tech/vscode-bash-vs-ssh-bash/</guid>
        <description>Kostya&#39;s Blog https://xni.github.io/tech/vscode-bash-vs-ssh-bash/ -&lt;p&gt;VSCode in interpreter returns /bin/bash, ssh - &amp;lsquo;-bash&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
- https://xni.github.io/tech/vscode-bash-vs-ssh-bash/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Will the exchanges survive?</title>
        <link>https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 22:17:11 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/</guid>
        <description>Kostya&#39;s Blog https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/ -&lt;p&gt;Citadel Securuties &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-04-01/ken-griffin-s-virus-plan-now-includes-emergency-site-in-florida&#34;&gt;placed&lt;/a&gt; its high profile traders to the isolated hotel in Florida. I am not saying this post will be an absolute truth. It is just a reflection of my knowledge about finance, how I have connected the dots of facts known by me to a broader picture. Perhaps, some guys like Ray Dalio etc etc have a better clarity about all of these, but I will try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why the exchanges remained open during the coronavirus outbreak?
I think the answer lies in the realization how deep we are drawn into the &amp;lsquo;investments&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investments were there for a very long time. Mostly in the form of fundraising:
trading ships, manufacturing and even wars. But what did it so crucial in our day to day lives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a step back. Can you imagine an old farmer of X-th century dreaming about passive income?
Probably, not. But actually he usually was doing a good investments in another way: children.
Seriously, if you have lots of children who are healthy, not lazy, strong, they will care
about you when you will get older. So helping them to grow up was a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, we moved from the agricultural society to the manufacturing one.
And capitalists entered the game. Generally, if you were able to accumulate some capital,
you can get some profits by running your factory, by creating jobs. And being a capitalist was
a way to create a passive income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on, some people realized, that even if you don&amp;rsquo;t have enough funds to open a
factory by your own, you can own a factory together. And here we are welcoming a
stock exchanges, first IPOs and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, things are logical to me.
So, what we observed was: we need exchanges in order to people who want to invest now,
in order to receive some money flow in the future, can meet each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea became so popular, that now everyone is an investor.
Because our goverments are literally telling us - you don&amp;rsquo;t have any other way
to have a chance to retire, other than being an investor. We will not care about you.
Your children will not care about you. Only participating in some capitalistic
businesses is a way to have your bread and water in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why the exchange in my opinion is equal to the capitalism.
If the goverment orders to close NASDAQ, it will move us back to square one.
It is the only allowed religion of current days: &amp;ldquo;in order to have passive
income - invest&amp;rdquo; (well, for average people, extraordinary guys have some other
options).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens some other interesting questions: how durable is this model? Generally,
if everyone will become an investor, investing 90% of their money to something,
how profitable it will be? If we will be spending money only on food,
what can we invest to? Only to agriculture.
These will be the only businesses. And then, you will also work
only there. It looks like a loop. And we are back to square 1. That&amp;rsquo;s why we
need some money spoiling habits, because they free some money from the system,
it is a way to create slavery from the people who prefer to spend now rather than
to save. Please, love them. They and their children will work in order to
make your retirement smooth and happy.&lt;/p&gt;
- https://xni.github.io/finance/will-exchange-survive/ - </description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 